<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.calstfrancis.rubric</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <name>Rubric</name>
  <summary>Worship service planning with RCL integration</summary>

  <description>
    <p>
      Rubric is a GNOME-native worship service planning tool for United Church
      of Canada ministry. Plan service orders, look up RCL readings, find
      hymns, fetch Bible passages, and export polished bulletins as HTML or PDF.
      PDF export uses the bundled Typst typesetter — no external tools required.
    </p>
    <p>Features include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Revised Common Lectionary readings, liturgical colour, and per-Proper hymn suggestions</li>
      <li>Hymn lookup from Voices United, More Voices, and Let Us Sing via Hymnary.org</li>
      <li>Bible passage viewer (WEB, KJV, ASV, ESV) with one-click scripture insertion</li>
      <li>Rich text and raw Typst editing per service element</li>
      <li>Live PDF bulletin preview with bundled Typst compiler</li>
      <li>HTML bulletin export — print to PDF directly from your browser</li>
      <li>Service Planner to browse and open all your saved services</li>
      <li>GitHub sync to back up and share services across machines</li>
      <li>Snippets library and responsive reading builder</li>
      <li>Named service order templates</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.calstfrancis.rubric.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/calstfrancis/rubric</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/calstfrancis/rubric/issues</url>

  <developer>
    <name>Caleb St. Francis</name>
  </developer>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.15.3" date="2026-06-08">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak fix: git sync (commit, push, pull) now works inside the sandbox via flatpak-spawn --host.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.2" date="2026-06-08">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak fix: the bundled Typst binary was not being found, silently breaking all PDF preview and export. Now installed to /app/bin where it is on PATH.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.1" date="2026-06-07">
      <description>
        <p>Bulletin and Manuscript preview toggle. Delete key no longer removes service elements while typing in a text field. Preview scroll position preserved across recompiles. Typst markup (italic, bold, headings) in element notes now renders correctly. Heading hierarchy fixed: = section, == element with rule, === sub-heading.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.0" date="2026-06-07">
      <description>
        <p>Phase 4 — Polish and Packaging. Typst syntax highlighting in the element editor (GtkSourceView). Structured error parsing for compilation failures. In-app Typst template editor in Preferences → Typst Files with Reset to default. Bundled typst binary included in deb and rpm packages. Documentation updated throughout.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.8" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Sidebar starts fully visible. Autosave restore dialog now appears after the changelog, not over it. Hymn downloads continue in the background if you close the wizard; toast notification when done. Hymn scraping now uses og:title for reliability.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.7" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Compact view now actually reduces row height. Fixes the CSS that was adding padding to divider rows and having no effect on service-item rows.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.4" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Native .deb (Debian/Ubuntu) and .rpm (openSUSE/Fedora) packages. Build scripts added: build-deb.sh and build-rpm.sh.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.12" date="2026-05-16">
      <description>
        <p>Service Planner, GitHub sync, redo support, translation selector (WEB/KJV/ASV/ESV), and HTML bulletin export.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.11" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Lectionary year tracker, per-Proper hymn suggestions, inline Hymnary preview, welcome dialog, and app renamed to Rubric.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.10" date="2026-03-01">
      <description>
        <p>Scripture layout improvements, PDF compile button, toast notifications, menu reorganisation.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <provides>
    <mediatype>application/x-liturgy</mediatype>
  </provides>

  <recommends>
    <display_length compare="ge">768</display_length>
  </recommends>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">600</display_length>
  </requires>
</component>
