<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.calstfrancis.rubric</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <name>Rubric</name>
  <summary>Worship service planning with RCL integration</summary>

  <description>
    <p>
      Rubric is a GNOME-native worship service planning tool for United Church
      of Canada ministry. Plan service orders, look up RCL readings, find
      hymns, fetch Bible passages, and export polished bulletins as HTML or PDF.
      PDF export uses the bundled Typst typesetter — no external tools required.
    </p>
    <p>Features include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Revised Common Lectionary readings, liturgical colour, and per-Proper hymn suggestions</li>
      <li>Hymn lookup from Voices United, More Voices, and Let Us Sing via Hymnary.org</li>
      <li>Bible passage viewer (WEB, KJV, ASV, ESV) with one-click scripture insertion</li>
      <li>Rich text and raw Typst editing per service element</li>
      <li>Live PDF bulletin preview with bundled Typst compiler</li>
      <li>HTML bulletin export — print to PDF directly from your browser</li>
      <li>Service Planner to browse and open all your saved services</li>
      <li>GitHub sync to back up and share services across machines</li>
      <li>Snippets library and responsive reading builder</li>
      <li>Named service order templates</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.calstfrancis.rubric.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/calstfrancis/rubric</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/calstfrancis/rubric/issues</url>

  <developer>
    <name>Caleb St. Francis</name>
  </developer>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.17.7" date="2026-06-23">
      <description>
        <p>0.17.7 "Tended Ground" — Service notes, justice bar, and unified dates editor.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Service Notes area: a collapsible text field above the service order for theology, metaphors, and movement notes. Not included in the bulletin. Pop-out button opens a floating window sharing the same buffer.</li>
          <li>Justice / observances bar: a second status bar row shows upcoming and recent social justice, indigenous, ecological, and pride observances as coloured chips.</li>
          <li>All dates — built-in observances and custom dates — are now editable in one unified spreadsheet. Reset to defaults at any time.</li>
          <li>Fixed: save button blue accent removed; PDF preview flicker reduced.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.6" date="2026-06-20">
      <description>
        <p>0.17.6 "Open Flow" — Two-column bulletin and manuscript exports now use regular multicolumn flow instead of a manual character-weight split.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Removed the heuristic that split items into left/right halves with an explicit column break; Typst now flows content naturally through #columns(2).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.5" date="2026-06-17">
      <description>
        <p>Bug-fix release: several long-standing Typst compile failures and a broken HTML export are resolved.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed: leader's order compile failed on any service element whose text ended with a line-break — the trailing backslash produced invalid Typst syntax that left the content block unclosed.</li>
          <li>Fixed: unmatched ] in liturgy content could prematurely close the surrounding columns block and cause a compile error.</li>
          <li>Fixed: "Could not show link" error when exporting to HTML — the file was written to a sandboxed location the browser could not access.</li>
          <li>Fixed: compile button required a prior manual Typst export; it now writes the file automatically.</li>
          <li>Compiled PDFs now open in the system viewer automatically after a successful build.</li>
          <li>Compile errors are now logged to ~/.cache/rubric/compile-error.log for easier diagnosis.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.4" date="2026-06-12">
      <description>
        <p>Accessibility improvements, visual polish, smart save, and live preview.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Smart save — "● Unsaved" chip in the status bar; auto-saves 2 seconds after you stop typing when a file is open.</li>
          <li>Live preview mode — instant HTML bulletin preview that bypasses Typst compilation.</li>
          <li>Quick help overlay — ? button in the header explains each area of the screen in plain English.</li>
          <li>First-launch wizard now asks for church name before the service-type choice.</li>
          <li>Section dividers show a coloured left-border stripe in their liturgical colour.</li>
          <li>Seasonal gradient strip and subtle header tint follow the liturgical season colour.</li>
          <li>Cover art thumbnail in the header when a cover image is configured.</li>
          <li>Service rows show both leader and note preview (e.g. "All · In the beginning…").</li>
          <li>Inline scripture preview — cached verse text appears as a subtitle on Scripture element rows.</li>
          <li>Empty service placeholder includes a "Start with lectionary" button.</li>
          <li>Friendly Typst error messages replace raw compiler output.</li>
          <li>Fixed: What's New changelog was not shown in installed flatpak builds.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.3" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Notes panel can now compress horizontally.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The notes/editor panel no longer has a hard minimum width — it compresses to give the preview panel space when needed.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.2" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Layout and window fixes.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>All four panels (sidebar, order, notes, preview) now share the window — no panel can push another off-screen or collapse it to zero.</li>
          <li>Window opens maximized by default.</li>
          <li>Multiple undo fixes: toggling bulletin visibility, editing the leader field, changing duration, and inserting scripture are all now undoable.</li>
          <li>Opening a file no longer wipes the current service if the new file is invalid.</li>
          <li>Hymn mode toolbar no longer flickers when switching elements.</li>
          <li>Tab mode inserts into the currently visible tab, not the last one.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.1" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Polish and hymn toggle.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Hymn toggle button in every element toolbar — activate to show hymn search and suggestions for any element, not just those named "Hymn".</li>
          <li>Inserted scripture passages display as readable text in the editor — no raw Typst visible.</li>
          <li>Focus mode now restores sidebar to its pre-focus state.</li>
          <li>Season colour applied to week name label and lectionary chip.</li>
          <li>Events in status bar spread further apart.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.17.0" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Major UX update: rich text editor, snippets manager, rubric section, and order panel polish.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Rich text editor — raw Typst mode removed; content is always edited as rich text.</li>
          <li>Rubric section — private leader-instructions area per element, manuscript-only.</li>
          <li>Snippets manager — full CRUD window with rich-text editing and tagging.</li>
          <li>Vertical section tabs on the order panel; season colour strip at panel top.</li>
          <li>Section divider rows styled as pills with section colour dot.</li>
          <li>Leader references (hymn numbers, scripture citations) shown as subtitle in order rows.</li>
          <li>Drag handles fade in on hover to reduce visual noise.</li>
          <li>Simple mode hides dev/git/time controls.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.16.0-rc5" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>UX polish across the service editor.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Suggestion pills now wrap to multiple rows with full titles — no horizontal scrolling.</li>
          <li>Status bar is slimmer; liturgical season colour dot added.</li>
          <li>Element type icons (music, scripture, prayer, sermon) in service order rows.</li>
          <li>Reading chips turn green after inserting a passage into the service.</li>
          <li>Calendar icon on date button for clearer affordance.</li>
          <li>Keyboard shortcut overlay accessible via Ctrl+?.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.16.0-rc4" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Hymn UI redesign and compact mode fix.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Hymn toolbar consolidated into a single button opening a three-tab popover: Lookup, By Title, By Theme.</li>
          <li>Theme popover enlarged — all 14 themes visible without scrolling; toggle-style chip selection.</li>
          <li>Suggestion strip redesigned as flat linked pills with inline YouTube button.</li>
          <li>Compact view now correctly reduces row height.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.7" date="2026-06-09">
      <description>
        <p>Documentation update: in-app Help and FAQ fully rewritten for Flatpak-only distribution. All references to pipx, pip, apt, zypper, dnf, system dependencies, LaTeX/xelatex, TeX Live, and conditional Typst or WebKit availability removed.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.6" date="2026-06-09">
      <description>
        <p>Status bar and UI polish.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Status bar across the bottom of the window with text-style toggle buttons (Zerkalo-style): SIMPLE, GOST, Focus, Git, and a version chip that opens the changelog</li>
          <li>GOST Type B engineering font bundled and applied globally when the GOST toggle is on</li>
          <li>Liturgical observance chips in the centre of the status bar — click any chip to open a built-in Wikipedia article window</li>
          <li>Focus mode button in the status bar — hides the palette and element list; status bar always remains accessible</li>
          <li>Git button — commit and push to GitHub with one click (pull --rebase runs first)</li>
          <li>Rubric now reopens the last file automatically on launch</li>
          <li>Hymn lookup redesigned as a linked pill (entry field + search button)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.5" date="2026-06-09">
      <description>
        <p>Bug fixes and UX polish: ESV translation no longer silently falls back to WEB; bulletin hymn Typst syntax corrected; bulletin toggle opacity works in tab view; bulletin save errors surfaced; hymn lookup injection is undoable; snippet button hidden in simple mode; ESV key saves live in Preferences; section-delete dialog corrected; all remaining "LaTeX" labels updated to "Typst".</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.4" date="2026-06-08">
      <description>
        <p>Delete key now works correctly in the element content editor — deletes the character to the right of the cursor rather than being swallowed by the window accelerator.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.3" date="2026-06-08">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak fix: git sync (commit, push, pull) now works inside the sandbox via flatpak-spawn --host.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.2" date="2026-06-08">
      <description>
        <p>Flatpak fix: the bundled Typst binary was not being found, silently breaking all PDF preview and export. Now installed to /app/bin where it is on PATH.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.1" date="2026-06-07">
      <description>
        <p>Bulletin and Manuscript preview toggle. Delete key no longer removes service elements while typing in a text field. Preview scroll position preserved across recompiles. Typst markup (italic, bold, headings) in element notes now renders correctly. Heading hierarchy fixed: = section, == element with rule, === sub-heading.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.15.0" date="2026-06-07">
      <description>
        <p>Phase 4 — Polish and Packaging. Typst syntax highlighting in the element editor (GtkSourceView). Structured error parsing for compilation failures. In-app Typst template editor in Preferences → Typst Files with Reset to default. Bundled typst binary included in deb and rpm packages. Documentation updated throughout.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.8" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Sidebar starts fully visible. Autosave restore dialog now appears after the changelog, not over it. Hymn downloads continue in the background if you close the wizard; toast notification when done. Hymn scraping now uses og:title for reliability.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.7" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Compact view now actually reduces row height. Fixes the CSS that was adding padding to divider rows and having no effect on service-item rows.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.4" date="2026-06-06">
      <description>
        <p>Native .deb (Debian/Ubuntu) and .rpm (openSUSE/Fedora) packages. Build scripts added: build-deb.sh and build-rpm.sh.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.12" date="2026-05-16">
      <description>
        <p>Service Planner, GitHub sync, redo support, translation selector (WEB/KJV/ASV/ESV), and HTML bulletin export.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.11" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Lectionary year tracker, per-Proper hymn suggestions, inline Hymnary preview, welcome dialog, and app renamed to Rubric.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.10" date="2026-03-01">
      <description>
        <p>Scripture layout improvements, PDF compile button, toast notifications, menu reorganisation.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <provides>
    <mediatype>application/x-liturgy</mediatype>
  </provides>

  <recommends>
    <display_length compare="ge">768</display_length>
  </recommends>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">600</display_length>
  </requires>
</component>
